TANGUS KINGDOM
The monk you sent
to find your wife is dead.
Did you hear?
When I was 9 years old...
my father took me to the
Merkit clan to choose a bride.
He stole my mother from the Merkits...
and they never forgot it.
Now he needed peace...
so I had to take a Merkit bride.
I couldn't say no to my father.
My friend Dai Sachen lives here.
Let's stop here for a night.
Welcome, my friend Esugei!
Good to see you.
Your son got big.
What's your name?
Temudgin.
It's me that should ask first.
How old are you?
Nine.
You're even younger than me.
By a lot?
By a whole year.
Why did you come here?
I'm going to the Merkits
to choose a bride.
I'm here for the night.
Smart people choose us for brides.
Goodbye, Temudgin.
Wait. What's your name?
Borte. Temudgin.
You should choose me!
Let's fight, Targutai!
I'm drunk, you can beat me.
You're not just a fool, you're weak.
These mosquitoes are hungry.
I want to look for a bride here.
This clan's weak.
People come here for brides.
I must make peace with the Merkits.
I want to practice.
You can't just practice.
They'll be offended.
If they're weak, let them be offended.
Listen carefully to what I tell you.
Don't make a mistake
when you choose a bride.
Her face has to be flat like a salt lake.
Her eyes have to be narrow.
Evil spirits dive into big eyes...
and she will go mad...
seeing things that aren't there.
And most important:
Don't forget to look at her legs.
A woman has to have strong legs...
to make a man happy.
Understand?
I choose you.
I agree.
I have chosen my bride.
I'll give a sable coat for her.
Your son made a good choice,
Esugei.
For sure, he saved us time.
We can ride back home now.
You're right!
For my clan, it is a great honor.
They can marry in five years.
This is a wishbone from a white raven.
Rub it and make your wish.
I'll be back in five years.
Why didn't you listen to me?
You're stubborn.
I saw her and I knew...
she's my wife.
What will I say to the Merkits now?
My head hurts thinking about it.
Merkits will never forget this offense.
We rode back home.
My father didn't talk.
Finally he said to me:
"You did good.
A man has to choose his wife."
I didn't know that day...
would change my life forever.
Scared?
Yes.
Thunder means...
our god Tengri is angry.
All Mongols are afraid of it.
Enemies.
So what?
You can't spill blood by a place of rest.
Accept this milk from my master.
Thanks. Sit.
Thank you.
Esugei, let the servant drink it first.
See how they're looking at us.
They're our enemies.
But if I, Khan Esugei,
start breaking the customs...
the world will turn upside down.
Are you sick, Esugei?
Let's stop.
Shut up! It's not for you to decide.
They've poisoned our khan!
You little bastard!
I'm leaving you, my son.
You'll be khan now.
Be strong...
and ask our lord
of the blue sky, great Tengri...
to help you.
Take everything!
Don't you dare!
That's the herd of your khan.
He protected you!
Get away from there!
Stop it!
You ungrateful piece of shit!
You're not afraid to steal, Targutai?
No. Khan Esugei is dead.
My son is khan now. He'll avenge us!
You want me to kill him?
Run! Quick!
Catch him!
Run!
You have the devil in you!
Targutai!
What's come over you?
Mongols don't kill children!
I curse you.
Rot in hell!
As Esugei said:
Never break the customs,
even if you want to.
When he grows up, I'll kill him.
He will grow up soon.
We'll come after him in the winter.
Someday...
you'll have to kill him.
But save yourself first.
That winter, I had no place to hide.
I went to the sacred mountain...
to ask our god Tengri to help me.
I was on my own.
The mountain was far away.
And I ran for my life.
Hey!
I'm Jamukha.
What's your name?
My name is Temudgin.
A Mongol has to be on a horse.
My enemy Targutai took all our horses.
You helped me, Jamukha.
Will you be my brother?
Taichar, give me a rag.
We're blood brothers now.
When I become khan, I'll
make you my second-in-command.
Jamukha...
I must kill my enemy, Targutai, first.
How can you? You have no horse.
My bride has strong legs.
Who cares about legs?
My father said it makes a man happy.
You need a horse more than a woman.
Run!
Targutai!
Tell people I don't want to be khan.
You're a dog.
Nobody cares about you anymore.
Why do you still want to kill me?
I'll sleep better.
I'll kill you!
I'll kill you first.
Bastard!
You need to be strong. Eat.
Drink.
These flies...
suck your blood.
Temudgin!
Your family is safe.
Don't worry.
Jamukha. Find my bride.
Tell her to wait for me.
He's still short.
Feed him more.
When I get back...
I want him grown.
Great Tengri, lord of the blue sky.
I bow before you.
Free me, great Tengri.
No matter how far the wolf runs...
he comes home one day.
Temudgin.
I've been waiting for you.
I'm khan now.
I'm smarter than your father.
He was a fool.
You call yourself khan?
Shit is always shit.
I won't just kill you.
I'll kill you piece by piece.
You see the wooden donkey?
I'll nail you to it myself!
It takes a week to die!
Come closer, old man.
You scare me.
If I don't die...
I'll forgive all of you.
You won't forgive any of us.
Come here.
Give me water.
You idiot.
Shut up!
I'll show you who's an idiot.
Don't move!
I'm Temudgin.
I'm Boorchu.
Why are you helping me?
I know who you are. Take my horse.
I won't forget you, Boorchu.
Great Tengri watched over me
and I survived.
I was ready to face my enemies...
and take back what was mine.
But first I had to find my bride, Borte.
I thought you were dead.
I'm not.
You know why I came.
You chose her years ago.
I don't know...
if Borte still wants you.
My Temudgin came back.
Father...
I have to go with Temudgin.
Bring the sable coat. Quick.
Don't you want to touch me,
Temudgin?
My touch will break you in two.
My son.
Temudgin.
I like you.
You're strong, like me.
You're good.
This is my dowry. Take it.
For me.
It's too much.
This is for you.
Brother, when will you put up your yurt?
Tomorrow.
It's good to have our brother back.
And with such a beautiful wife.
I caught you.
Only because I let you.
I'll make a good wife.
I know.
Stay here!
Oelun!
Chiledu?
You remember my voice?
A woman never forgets her first husband.
Get down. I want to see your face.
Why should I look at you,
old woman?
I want Temudgin's bride.
Get out of here. Leave us alone!
They're not here!
Go!
Shut up!
Khasar, watch out!
Where are they?
Speak!
I found their tracks.
Let's go!
Temudgin, I waited so long for you.
I rubbed this wishbone
so many times.
I had only one wish.
That you would come back.
I always want to be with you, Temudgin.
I promise.
Merkits.
Go home!
When Temudgin's father...
stole my bride...
I swore revenge.
You're mine now.
Take her!
My son.
My brother.
What did they do to you?
How are you, Jamukha, my brother?
I'm glad you're alive, brother.
Accept my gift, brother.
When I heard that the Merkits
had stolen your wife...
my liver began to ache.
I want to talk to you.
Mongols don't make war over a woman.
I'll tell Taichar now and
he'll bring you two new wives.
I want Borte back.
Temudgin, have you
never tried another one?
And you think she's the only one
with strong legs?
My time is short.
Say welcome.
Taichar...
Merkits have offended my brother.
How many warriors can you bring?
I have my sword and some people.
That's not enough, brother.
That's why I came to you.
I'll do it.
Next year.
That's too late.
Next year's better.
We wait.
Don't tell anyone we went to war
over a woman.
This is Merkit territory.
Who the hell are you?
I knew you would come for me.
Borte, I can't stay away from you.
This is my son.
I see.
Are you happy to have your wife back?
I wouldn't sleep with such a woman.
You're brave.
Very brave!
I want to thank you, brother.
You'll stay with me now.
I'm used to being my own master.
You don't know Mongols.
You won't survive on your own.
You'll be my second-in-command.
Temudgin, your people are waiting.
I have to go.
Go.
Temudgin, I grabbed
the best sword for you.
Jamukha took most of the plunder.
Tell us how to divide what's left.
I'll take a tenth portion.
Divide the rest between the warriors.
Don't forget the families
of the warriors who died.
This is for you.
Thank you, Temudgin.
Listen, everyone.
Temudgin is generous to us.
Everyone gets their share.
Look at him.
He gave away all his plunder.
Next time he'll take it all.
He's taking a Merkit child into his yurt.
Don't speak ill of my brother.
What brother is he to you?
I'm your brother.
You can't cook two ram heads
in one pot...
Temudgin.
Wake up.
My brother left me.
He's stubborn.
Get up!
Daritai!
Altan!
Taichar.
Where's Daritai?
Where's Altan?
They should be close to my boots.
They left with Temudgin.
What?
Brother.
You didn't say goodbye to me.
You were sleeping, brother.
My people are with you now.
Why, brother?
Mongols change their masters
when they want to.
Daritai.
Altan.
Why have you deserted me?
Temudgin...
is fair to his warriors.
Give us back our horses!
You gave me this horse, so it's mine.
Daritai, I'm the law.
I'll tear your rotting liver out.
Try.
My liver...
has a new master now!
I can't send them back to you, brother.
Mongols have the right to choose.
Look after our horse. I'll be back!
Daritai! Thieves are stealing
Temudgin's horses!
Jamukha's people
tried to steal your horses.
We killed one of them.
One less thief.
We killed Jamukha's brother.
Taichar.
Who killed him?
I did.
I didn't recognize him.
You saved the horses...
but you brought us war.
Forgive me, lord.
Send my head to Jamukha.
He guarded your herd well.
If you hand him over,
what will people say?
I've heard of your sorrow,
Jamukha.
I'll help you get revenge.
I want to tie Temudgin's head
to the tail of my horse.
Do it.
Without you...
I can't.
Are you afraid, Targutai?
What kind of khan are you?
There are only two strong Mongols
in the steppe.
Me...
and my brother Temudgin.
Understand?
I'll bring all my horsemen.
Give me Temudgin!
Temudgin, Jamukha
is following your tracks.
There will be 10 of them
for each of us.
Tell us what to do.
I won't leave our families behind.
If we save ourselves,
we can come back for them.
It's the only way.
Altan, Daritai. You trusted me
with your families.
Jamukha will show them no mercy.
Are you ready to abandon them?
You decide, Temudgin.
Temudgin.
Leave us.
Save yourself.
Do as all Mongols do.
Everyone will understand.
Not me.
Go to the mountains, quick!
Let's move, Jamukha.
What are you waiting for?
What's the rush, Targutai?
Temudgin will run away.
We'll never find him.
You don't know my brother.
- Are you ready?
- Ready, Temudgin.
Khasar.
Take enough men
to protect our families.
Temudgin, we're staying with you.
It's time to go.
Look after yourself and our son.
Stay alive, Temudgin.
Don't forget us.
You see how smart my brother is?
It won't be easy to take him.
Attack!
I want Temudgin alive.
Me too.
You promised, he's mine.
Everything here is mine, Targutai.
And you're mine too.
You say nothing.
At least beg me for mercy.
You want to die, Temudgin?
I'm not a beggar, brother.
Beg me for your life.
I can't.
I'm asking you.
Forgive me, brother.
I'm not your brother.
I'm your khan.
And you are my slave!
Take him.
Hold on.
I can't go on.
Forgive me, I lost the battle.
You fought well.
You saved our families.
Now Mongols know your name,
Temudgin.
Get up.
Go! Push!
I'm finished.
How are you, garrison chief?
Stop here.
Want to buy slaves?
How much?
One rope of Tangut money.
That one is two.
And that one...
five ropes.
Too high. Three.
I can't go lower.
This one killed my best guard.
Don't buy that one.
He will bring sorrow upon us.
What sorrow can a slave bring?
We have thousands of them.
He'll never forgive
the humiliation. Let him go.
Foolish talk, old monk.
He's a slave, and he'll die a slave.
I see hordes of Mongol horsemen...
ravaging your land, death.
Hey, Mongol.
You want to destroy my kingdom?
I know what to do with him.
I haven't been paid in months.
Listen.
Let's sell the beast.
Who'd buy him?
Hey, Mongol! Show us your teeth.
MONGOL WHO WANTED
TO DESTROY TANGUT KINGDOM
Forgive us.
Mongols die in cages.
I'm alive.
Your spirit is strong.
I am here to ask you...
when the terrible time comes...
do not destroy our monastery.
Kill the guard tonight...
bring me the key.
My faith does not allow me to kill.
My faith does.
The monastery has many sacred books.
They must be saved.
I can't read.
Go to the merchants
who trade with Mongols.
Ask them to find Temudgin's clan
and give this bone to Borte.
Remember, Borte.
I'll do it.
In Mongolia, everyone gets robbed.
Among us merchants,
only Golden Earring goes there.
But he's a thief himself.
Nobody knows when he comes...
or when he goes.
Nobody can help you, old monk.
Juchi. Juchi.
We must go.
I know how to bury a monk.
What are you waiting for?
A caravan.
I'm the last caravan...
and I won't be back soon.
Take us with you now!
It's a long road.
I can see you have no money.
How will you pay me?
You know how I'll pay you.
Not enough.
We had a deal.
He wants more.
Or he'll tell on me.
I haven't got any more.
You don't look like a poor woman.
I want to talk to you.
Don't try to cross me.
Give me the key.
What's her name?
Mongen.
I am your father, Mongen.
Where is my other father?
Forget him.
This is your father now.
Go and sleep.
Don't worry, he's our father.
Do you want to play too?
Father.
Why don't you braid your hair?
Shouldn't a man always braid his hair?
Not me.
We call this "meat."
Meat.
Our language is the most beautiful.
Someday, everyone
will understand Mongol.
Listen to how beautiful it sounds:
Meat.
Juchi, how old are you?
Ten, Father.
You must choose a bride soon.
How do I choose?
I will teach you...
because finding a good woman
is the hardest thing.
I agree.
I told you not to be scared.
I'm not scared.
Our father is very funny.
I have names for the sons
you will bear me.
Don't you know
what Mongols are like?
I'm Mongol. I know.
They are worse than ever.
All they do is kill and steal.
They don't even spare the children.
I know what to do with Mongols.
Take the children and go home.
When will you be back?
A year?
Two years?
I won't see you soon, Temudgin.
Lord of the blue sky, great Tengri.
I bow before you.
Give me the strength.
Mongols need laws.
I will make them obey...
even if I have to kill half of them.
Our laws will be simple.
Don't kill women or children.
Don't forget your debts.
Fight enemies to the end.
And never betray your khan.
Many warriors came under my banner.
They knew I wanted to
unite all Mongols...
to make us strong.
But Jamukha tried to tear us apart.
The time came...
for our final battle to decide...
who would rule Mongolia.
Jamukha's army was bigger.
But I had my strategy...
and I knew how to win.
I still needed Tengri...
lord of the blue sky...
to be on my side.
My brother's warriors shoot well.
Let's attack, Jamukha.
My brother...
is crafty as a wolf.
First detachment.
Attack!
Go!
Temudgin.
We throw our khan at your feet.
He tried to run, but we killed him.
Who is this?
Your enemy, Targutai.
Kill them.
For what?
Altan!
What did we do wrong?
You broke the law.
You betrayed your khan.
We didn't know!
How are you, old man?
Thank you for remembering,
Khan Temudgin.
Give him 100 horses
and put his yurt next to mine.
Take all these men into my army.
Temudgin. We caught him.
Temudgin.
Now you're khan and I'm at your feet.
Are you happy?
I forgive you, brother.
It's too late.
I'll always be a rock in your boot.
I want to ask you:
All Mongols fear the thunder...
but not you?
I had no place to hide
from the thunder...
so I wasn't afraid anymore.
What are you going to
do with me, Temudgin?
What would you do?
I would kill me, brother.
Go.
You're letting your enemy go.
I'm letting my brother go.
Father!
When will we go to choose my bride?
You must keep your promise.
We'll go soon.
See how well I chose your mother.
Temudgin, I chose you.
True!
I have to finish what I started.
You're a good wife, Borte.
You know I'll always come back.
Old man...
tell me, what's my future?
Don't be afraid.
You know your future, great khan.
[ENGLISH]